<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Privacy on this&#39;n&#39;that</title>
		<link>https://szab.it/tags/privacy/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Privacy on this&#39;n&#39;that</description>
		<generator>Hugo 0.123.7 -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 10:42:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://szab.it/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>TrueNAS &amp; Nextcloud</title>
			<link>https://szab.it/posts/truenas-and-nextcloud/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2022 10:42:00 +0200</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://szab.it/posts/truenas-and-nextcloud/</guid>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Awhile back I wrote about my experience in running &lt;a href=&#34;https://szab.it/posts/time-travel-and-privacy/&#34;&gt;TrueNAS and Nextcloud&lt;/a&gt; server
at home. Thought I would give a small update how is that after 1.5 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still very happy with the whole setup, even extended storage in the server.
Had some interesting experiences when I tried to upgrade Plex and Nextcloud
jails. There I just gave up, I still update and upgrade them, but not via
TrueNAS&amp;rsquo; update functionality, but by logging into the instance and issuing the
update commands in the container. Also before updating I always make backups of
them using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.truenas.com/docs/core/storage/snapshots/&#34;&gt;snapshot feature&lt;/a&gt; and when I managed to fubar my Nextcloud
instance it was just ~4 clicks to restore it to normal without losing data or
settings or anything. It is quite fiddly, still didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to figure out how
am I going to upgrade the MySQL in that container. Tried to just use the
system&amp;rsquo;s package manager, but that didn&amp;rsquo;t turn out well.. So might gonna
re-create a new instance and just migrate settings and mounts over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managed to discover a &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.nextcloud.com/apps/news&#34;&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt; for Nextcloud recently that manages RSS feeds and
has also an &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=de.luhmer.owncloudnewsreader&#34;&gt;Android app&lt;/a&gt;, so that it can keep track of read and unread news no
matter where the reading happened. Pretty much like feedly (used that service
before finding this), so I can read some articles on the computer and those will
be also marked as read on the mobile. Writing it down it feels like a laughable
feature, but its really convenient! (one less google owned service that I use)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only grievance with Nextcloud is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nextcloud/android/pull/9981&#34;&gt;regression in their mobile app&lt;/a&gt; that they
are really slow on fixing it. The issue is about that once you sync photos from
Nextcloud to your phone, then the mobile&amp;rsquo;s gallery app won&amp;rsquo;t see them properly,
so you cannot use those photos in other apps. E.g. would like to crop and only
send the cropped image to someone on discord, well then you&amp;rsquo;re out of luck..
have to edit it on the computer.. and since I&amp;rsquo;m on the computer, might as well
send it from there.. Not a deal breaker bug, but it is annoying. Like this
Nextcloud for my wife is only about backup and easy access on the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over to backup feature of TrueNAS. Those files that are important to me and they
are not in Nextcloud (e.g. full family photo collection) I setup TrueNAS to do
daily cloud backups. I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.backblaze.com/b2/cloud-storage.html&#34;&gt;Backblaze&lt;/a&gt; for it and like this I have an offsite
backup for ~7 USD/month for all those files that are truly important. Also
TrueNAS can do encrypted backups, so if the worst would happen and Backblaze
would get hacked, then still nobody would have to see pictures of me sipping
beer in my underwear. :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post I have mentioned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nextcloud 11 times and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TrueNAS 7 number of times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe to say that I&amp;rsquo;m very happy with this setup and that I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to
repurposed an old PC that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t really get otherwise any use.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Time travel and privacy</title>
			<link>https://szab.it/posts/time-travel-and-privacy/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 18:39:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://szab.it/posts/time-travel-and-privacy/</guid>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;In December of 2020 I read some articles that made me want to go back in time
and use tools that I considered to be old. One of these articles was about the
productivity score by Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s O365, another was about how our phones betray
our trust (no surprise there).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content behind the following three links that made me think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2020/nov/26/microsoft-productivity-score-feature-criticised-workplace-surveillance&#34;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2020/nov/26/microsoft-productivity-score-feature-criticised-workplace-surveillance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WolfieChristl/status/1331221942850949121&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/WolfieChristl/status/1331221942850949121&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nrkbeta.no/2020/12/03/my-phone-was-spying-on-me-so-i-tracked-down-the-surveillants&#34;&gt;https://nrkbeta.no/2020/12/03/my-phone-was-spying-on-me-so-i-tracked-down-the-surveillants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mail-and-calendar&#34;&gt;Mail and Calendar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading the article about O365 and that GSuite also has something similar
to that, I decided to go back to some kind of e-mail and calendar application
like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thunderbird.net/&#34;&gt;Thunderbird&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.gnome.org/users/evolution/stable/&#34;&gt;Evolution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes I did use O365 via the browser before, it worked actually quite well didn&amp;rsquo;t
miss notifications and it overall provided a good interface. But using the
browser it also means that they can track:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;where is my mouse on the screen,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if the tab is actually active on my screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what is on my screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;typing and deleting and typing&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So really waaaay too much information that I would feel comfortable to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Must say it here: I&amp;rsquo;m not working for a company that collects such information
or would do actions based on such information. If the company would change and
go in this direction then I would have the choice to change my employer. Still I
would rather avoid providing even the possibility for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looked through possible e-mail clients for GNU/Linux, there were two things that
are a must have for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no electron apps - don&amp;rsquo;t want to run a full browser with nodejs.. just don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to be able to integrate with a calendar app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checked &lt;a href=&#34;https://bluemail.me/&#34;&gt;BlueMail&lt;/a&gt; briefly, but fall short on &lt;em&gt;a)&lt;/em&gt; being an electron app and &lt;em&gt;b)&lt;/em&gt; not
really maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looked at Thunderbird, it is still an okay with &lt;a href=&#34;https://addons.thunderbird.net/en-US/thunderbird/addon/lightning/&#34;&gt;Lightning&lt;/a&gt; it can also satisfy
the calendar and it is still the default e-mail client in Ubuntu. While I don&amp;rsquo;t
use Ubuntu this will still keep maintainers motivated. However Thunderbird just
didn&amp;rsquo;t feel right to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly I tried Evolution. After installing and setting it up, realized that I
used to use this client back when I started programming in 2010. Suddenly I&amp;rsquo;m
back in 2010, just have more grey hair than I used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With evolution it was a huge surprise to me that it works with O365 out of the
box, syncs calendar, contacts and even the todo items (if I would use them..
org-mode FTW!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: MS did admit this wasn&amp;rsquo;t a good way and they are going to remove some low
level reporting. See their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/blog/2020/12/01/our-commitment-to-privacy-in-microsoft-productivity-score/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;chat-applications&#34;&gt;Chat applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay this is bit of different topic than MS and phones tracking all of our
moves, but still related to the back in time theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By moving my e-mail and calendar to an app I managed to close two pinned tabs
from my browser and also managed to avoid using container tabs to be able to
login to my son&amp;rsquo;s and daughter&amp;rsquo;s O365 account (they are in lower grades of
primary school, so yes I do get to manage their accounts for when we&amp;rsquo;re in
remote tuition mode). With this closing of tabs I noticed that there are other
tabs that I also use they are just constantly pinned: whatsapp, facebook chat,
discord and sometimes gitter. So this provided a new challenge: can I find an
app to unite them all? Yes I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again didn&amp;rsquo;t wanted to use something that is just another browser, so went with
an old-old friend &lt;a href=&#34;https://pidgin.im/&#34;&gt;Pidgin&lt;/a&gt;. All the listed chat platforms have a plugin for it,
open source with a clean code base (didn&amp;rsquo;t review all of the code, but all the
files I visited was clean and relatively easy to understand), so very much
tempting to contribute. Best of all: Pidgin will only eat up ~70 Mb of memory -
opposed to gigabytes - and won&amp;rsquo;t send statistics about me to the facebook and
other data hoarder and dealers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mobile-front&#34;&gt;Mobile front&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this has triggered the privacy demon in me so started to look for
alternatives as well on mobile. First big hoarder to tackle: Google. The app
that is actual for me to look at is Google Photos. I loved this app as made
it very easy for me to share pictures with my wife or with anyone. Also could
access all the photos on my computer quickly and all is backed up and safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All good things must come to an end at some point for me with Google Photos the
end meant that - understandably - they don&amp;rsquo;t provide free storage anymore. In
the past if you accepted that they re-compress the images with their algorithms,
then they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t count towards used data - so free and unlimited storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos are actually a long story for me, tried a lot of different solutions when
dealing with photos from my camera. Nothing work truly easily. A new motivation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;apart of google - was that my wife started to make photos and videos with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the family DSLR. My wife isn&amp;rsquo;t tech savvy, so whatever solution I try next it
has to be seamless to her, other way she won&amp;rsquo;t use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to the solution: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.truenas.com/download-tn-core/&#34;&gt;TrueNAS&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, decided to run my own storage at home. As you
may already guess I didn&amp;rsquo;t go with the most straightforward solution&amp;hellip; nah life
would be boring if we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t make is pointlessly over complicated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for NAS my criteria was that I want to be able to extend it later when and if
I need more storage. For this you need more than just a two bay NAS, but rather
a 4 or 5 bay NAS. Now those bigger NAS setups a for me just ridiculously
expensive. Instead of spending big, decided to reuse my desktop PC from 2008 to
build a NAS using TrueNAS system. It is really an awesome setup for me, but
think I&amp;rsquo;ll write about that in a dedicated post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this TrueNAS setup I also installed &lt;a href=&#34;https://nextcloud.com/&#34;&gt;Nextcloud&lt;/a&gt;, this is able to replace both
Google Photos and Dropbox for me. Got a mobile app for it, easy enough to use
and there is also a Gnome integration for it. Apart of images and files it can
also serve as a calendar and contacts server (another stab at Google).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For larger files also configured NFS endpoints so that we can handle images from
the DSLR. NFS works surprisingly well with Darktable, it is able to read the
files quickly enough. If I would deal with images as a profession would probably
invest into a better network setup, but it works well enough via WiFi already.
Only secret is to keep &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.darktable.org/&#34;&gt;Darktable&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s SQLight database files on the local system,
having that over NFS renders the app uselessly slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the above setup working reliable and well, I&amp;rsquo;m really considering going
back to a privacy oriented Android setup on my phone as well, without all the
bloatware and mandatory google applications installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;news-sources&#34;&gt;News sources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSS is still out there and still lives, I was surprised to find that most news
sites will have RSS feeds as well. With RSS again one can use a simple
application, even Evolution has RSS reader plugin and have all the news tracking
free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;outro&#34;&gt;Outro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey with all those apps and different setups made me realize again that
we do share a lot of information about ourselves on the internet. In the
background we have no idea how they use all that data. The collected data
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be connectable the person behind it, but in truth it can be. If you
don&amp;rsquo;t read all the three articles linked in the beginning, just read &lt;a href=&#34;https://nrkbeta.no/2020/12/03/my-phone-was-spying-on-me-so-i-tracked-down-the-surveillants/&#34;&gt;Martin
Gundersen&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What gets measured gets managed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the data that we submit knowingly or not, voluntarily or not, will
enable companies to manage our actions. So now I&amp;rsquo;m back in 2010, running my own
server and using native application instead of browser based solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
