<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>practices on this&#39;n&#39;that</title>
		<link>https://szab.it/tags/practices/</link>
		<description>Recent content in practices on this&#39;n&#39;that</description>
		<generator>Hugo 0.69.2 -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 09:22:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="https://szab.it/tags/practices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<item>
			<title>MongoDB deprecating &#34;count&#34;</title>
			<link>https://szab.it/posts/mongodb-deprecating-count/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 09:22:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://szab.it/posts/mongodb-deprecating-count/</guid>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;Prior warning: this post may turn into a rant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;prologue&#34;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the second half of 2019 at my company we have got an expected notice from our
MongoDB provider, Atlas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notice was about the usual pain that they do every now and then: force
upgrade for old versions. At that time we were running MongoDB v3.4 and so now
we got the notice to ensure that we have a driver that supports v3.6 as all the
clusters will be upgraded on the end of January 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All is well we look at these upgrades as a necessary evil, that causes pain in
short therm, but will bring benefits in the long run. The benefits with newer
MongoDB versions was the performance. We have tested some of our heavier
queries - with which we already have had issues in production - and behold they
become 10 times faster. (We were comparing MongoDB v3.4 with v4.2 at that time)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thought cool 10x the power! Lets do this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have started our long journey of upgrades, tests, fixes and further
upgrades and tests, tears and cries, laughter and anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were satisfied with the upgrade we have deployed our first services,
that was already in need of that performance boost. Cool we thought, surely we
gonna have some co-workers coming to us saying: Boys don&amp;rsquo;t know what has
happened, but the service is blazing fast!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, we were wrong! Surely the queries looked fast, but there was a tiny bit of
issue: some of our calls to the database started to timeout. Worst of it those
calls were actually fast previously. As an icing on the cake this didn&amp;rsquo;t come to
our attention straightaway, but only a week later, when another new service
wanted to sync data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once noted, we jumped into debugging. Looking at the database&amp;rsquo;s real time
operations (&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.mongodb.com/manual/reference/method/db.currentOp/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;db.currentOp()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) we were seeing &lt;code&gt;aggregation&lt;/code&gt; calls on the biggest
collection being called. As we didn&amp;rsquo;t recall to have used such heavy
aggregations on that collection, we searched through our code base to find what
could issue this command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have managed to find a couple of places where we have used aggregation, but
none of them fitted the match that we seen in the operations list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually one team member suggested that that aggregation is the way MongoDB
does the count. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe it at first, but then we have read a bit more
about the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.mongodb.com/manual/reference/method/db.collection.countDocuments/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;countDocuments&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; method that was &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;suggested method by the
documentation&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; to use instead of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.mongodb.com/manual/reference/method/db.collection.countDocuments/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and turned out that it is indeed
slower as it is more accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From MongoDB&amp;rsquo;s JIRA ticket &lt;a href=&#34;https://jira.mongodb.org/browse/NODE-1638&#34;&gt;NODE-1638&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;count has been deprecated for a number of reasons. First, and foremost, the
existing count command could not be run within transactions, so an alternative
approach needed to be taken. Secondarily, the count command in most cases was
not accurate. We have replaced count with countDocuments and
estimatedDocumentCount. Please use estimatedDocumentCount for the performance
you are looking for, and parity with the original count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the reasons against &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not giving accurate results and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not transaction friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my point of view those two are not really reasons to deprecate a core
command, which think is quite needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;count-is-not-accurate&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; is not accurate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay it isn&amp;rsquo;t, but honestly what was accurate in MongoDB before? Like with
iterating a &lt;code&gt;cursor&lt;/code&gt; (with mongoose &lt;code&gt;stream&lt;/code&gt;), you could easily miss documents or
see others twice in the process. Unless you set read preference to snapshot, but
even then if the process is long running and you have inserts in the mean time,
then you won&amp;rsquo;t see the new documents, so it is still a &lt;em&gt;meh&lt;/em&gt; solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For processing all the data in the database, even the ones that didn&amp;rsquo;t exist
when we started the process, we were using a practice where we sorted the &lt;code&gt;_id&lt;/code&gt; in
ascending order, retrieving data in batches and using the last _id in the list
with a greater than filter: &lt;code&gt;{ _id: { $gt: lastId } }&lt;/code&gt;. Like this we could
processes all the documents without duplicates and if there were new documents
created while the process run, no problem, still got them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in case of the count, so far I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen a case where would have needed
pinpoint accuracy. I can imagine that there are case where one needs it, but
then just like with the streaming above there is a solution for it. The solution
in this case comes in aggregation and I&amp;rsquo;m sure that before the &lt;code&gt;countDocuments&lt;/code&gt;
command developers were using it to get the accurate count that they have
needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is nice that now there is a method in mongo, that can give you the accurate
count, without fiddling around with aggregation. It is convenient for those who
need it. Still in my point it is not a reason to deprecate &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-transaction-safe&#34;&gt;Not transaction safe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well okay. It isn&amp;rsquo;t. Don&amp;rsquo;t know, never tried it. As I tend to work with
microservices, I never missed or wanted to use transactions. It is hard to
implement across services. My preference for data consistency is to make
operations idempotent and so it is safe to put them into job queues, that
guarantee to run it at least once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to emphasize it: I do respect that in some cases transactions could be the
best or only solutions and it is nice that &lt;code&gt;countDocuments&lt;/code&gt; is transaction safe.
Just still not a reason to deprecate &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;solution&#34;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; has been marked as deprecated in MongoDB v4.0, it is still well and
alive in v4.2. Since the two replacement suggested to be used instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;countDocuments&lt;/code&gt; - way too slow for us&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;estimatedDocumentCount&lt;/code&gt; - cannot provide a query&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;are both unsuitable for us, we have reverted all our calls to use the poor old
&lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; method and we have accepted that our terminal will be showing the
deprecation warnings for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now we hope that they won&amp;rsquo;t remove it or they will improve the performance
of the new &lt;code&gt;countDocuments&lt;/code&gt; method to be on pair with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;finale&#34;&gt;Finale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, this has indeed become a rant, but you have been warned. :D Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Git global ignore file</title>
			<link>https://szab.it/posts/git-global-ignore-file/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 11:08:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<guid isPermaLink="true">https://szab.it/posts/git-global-ignore-file/</guid>
			<description>&lt;p&gt;the repo and you don&amp;rsquo;t even want it to be listed in the &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file of the
repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have multiple repositories, then there is a nice way to do it per user,
using the core.excludesFile config property of git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might be set in your git install already (it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the case for me, but
still worth to check it):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;git config --global --get core.excludesFile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If it returns path to a file, then just simply add your ignore pattern to that
file (just a todo.md line will do the trick, no need for absolute paths).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other way if the property isn&amp;rsquo;t set, you can set it to any file you would like
it to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;git config --global --add core.excludesFile ~/.myGitHideout
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Source for the solution: &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/gitignore&#34;&gt;https://git-scm.com/docs/gitignore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally I&amp;rsquo;ve posted this on medium as an answer to &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@dave%5Flunny/exclude-files-from-git-without-committing-changes-to-gitignore-986fa712e78d&#34;&gt;Dave Lunny&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt; in
2017/02/11.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
